Guide to the David Simon Blondheim papers, 1924-1981 K0007
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
David Simon Blondheim papers
1924-1981 and undated
1928-1934
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Dulles, Eleanor Lansing
Blondheim, David Simon
K0007
0.5 Linear Feet 1 document box
The papers of David Simon Blondheim (1884-1934) contain correspondence, typescripts, proofs, photographs, bookplates, notes, and other personal documents. The material dates from 1924 to 1981, with the bulk of the material dating between 1928 and 1934. Blondheim was a U.S. Romance scholar, renowned in his field for his work on medieval French and French linguistics. The material in this collection deals predominately with his work on medieval Jewish manuscripts and Judeo-Romance languages.
Biographical / Historical
David Simon Blondheim (1884-1934) was a U.S. philologist and scholar of medieval French and French linguistics. He was renowned in his field for his work on medieval Jewish manuscripts and Judeo-Romance languages.
Born in Baltimore, Maryland August 25, 1884, he received his AB at The Johns Hopkins University in 1906 and his Ph.D. in 1910. He later studied in France at the Sorbonne, the Collège de France, the École des Hautes Études, and the École des Chartes. In 1924 he became professor of Romance philology at Johns Hopkins University, and in 1926 he was awarded the Volney prize from the Académie des Inscriptions et Belles Lettres for his book Les Parlers Judeo-Romans et la Vetus Latina (1925). He was the first American to receive this honor.
David Blondheim was married to Eleanor Lansing Dulles, with whom he had one son, David Dulles. He died in Baltimore, March 19, 1934.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, typescripts, proofs, photographs, bookplates, notes, and other personal documents. The material dates from 1924 to 1981, with the bulk of the material dating between 1928 and 1934. These are the personal papers of philologist David Simon Blondheim. Blondheim was a U.S. Romance scholar, and the material in this collection deals predominately with his work on medieval Jewish manuscripts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers of David Simon Blondheim in this collection were found amongst the personal papers of his wife, Eleanor Lansing Dulles (MS2217). Dulles donated her papers, along with her professional library, to Eckles Library at Mount Vernon College, circa 1993. The George Washington University acquired the college's property and legacy in 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Related Materials
The majority of David Simon Blondheim's manuscripts and papers are housed in the Jewish National and University Library (now the National Library of Israel) in Jerusalem.
Additional photographs of Blondheim are found in the personal papers of his wife, Eleanor Lansing Dulles: MS2217. A catalogue of David S. Blondheim's professional library, containing works in the fields of romance philology, Hebraica, rare dictionaries, periodicals, reprints, and dissertations, may be found in the Gelman Library's online catalog: PC41.D85 1935.
Jewish literature; Judaism; Hebrew literature -- Bibliography; Romance philology -- Bibliography; Linguistics; Manuscripts, Medieval; Dulles, Eleanor Lansing
- Correspondence, 1929-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondents include Irving Brown of the Department of Romance Languages at Columbia University, the publisher D.C. Heath and Company, George Alexander Kohut, Dr. S. Hillel Blondheim, Dr. J. Jud Zollikon, Rabbi Samuel Fredman, Johns Hopkins University President Joseph Ames, Alexander Marx, Daniel V. Thompson, Jr., M. Ginsburger, and the Macmillan Company. Some signatures indecipherable.
- "Les Gloses Françaises dans les commentaires talmudiques de Raschi" Vol. 2--Publication, 1929-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  This folder contains proofs for the introductory material for "Les gloses Françaises dans les commentaires talmudiques de Raschi," published posthumously through the efforts of Blondheim's wife, Eleanor Lansing Dulles, and a related letter.
- "Liste des manuscrits des commentaires bibliques de Raschi"--Typescript, circa 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Livro de Como se Fazen as Cores"--Proofs, 10/03/1929 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  This folder contains proofs for Blondheim's article, "Livro de Como se Fazen as Cores," with editing marks, possibly by Daniel V. Thompson, Jr.
- "An Old Portuguese Work on Manuscript Illuminations"--Manuscript, Notes, Correspondence, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  This folder contains material pertaining to an article written by Blondheim, "An Old Portuguese Work on Manuscript Illuminations," for the Jewish Quarterly Review. Materials include a letter and corrections from Daniel V. Thompson, Jr., a typescript of the article with notes for the printer (Hebrew characters hand-written), and typed notes.
- "Les Parlers Judeo-Romans et la Vetus Latina"--Typescript, circa 1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photograph and Bookplates, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  This folder contains a photograph of David Simon Blondheim, and examples of his personal bookplate.
- Miscellaneous, 1925-1933 and undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  This folder contains fragmentary notes, a tuition bill from Johns Hopkins University, a hand-written outline of "Modern Jewish History," postcards, a typed teaching schedule, a typescript of a book review, and a reprint from PMLA of "A Bibliography of the Publications of David S. Blondheim" by H. H. Shapiro.
- Article by Dr. S.H. Blondheim, dedicated to D.S. Blondheim, 11/25/1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  This folder contains an article written by David Simon Blondheim's son, Dr. S. Hillel Blondheim, and an accompanying letter.
- "Catalogue of the Library of The Late David S. Blondheim: Collections in the fields of Romance Philology, Hebraica, rare dictionaries, periodicals, reprints, and dissertations", undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  General
  Prepared by Eleanor Dulles Blondheim and assistants